Hello and welcome to 2026 release wave 2
launch edition of what's new in server
and database. My name is Kenny Pabidan.
I'm a program manager here in business
central and with me I have mascot. Yeah,
I'm the manager of the runtime team
>> and uh we have put together a packed
agenda starting with AL runtime going
through all the way down to security
features. So um mass why don't you take
us through the AL runtime?
>> Yeah, thank you Kenny. So with this
version the NST now runs on .NET 10, the
latest and greatest in the net um that
brings all the great things of .NET 10.
You can read more about that online. Um
and then another thing we did and uh
this was one of my colleagues uh this
was actually input from a custom case
where they were hitting some out of
memory exceptions. Um so now we're using
a streaming based implementation for
open Excel way more way less memory
usage when you want to open up big uh
excels um and less out of memory
exception. You can now load even bigger
ones. What a great feature.
And finally uh the recent records is
something we have added that you can see
in the UI when you are opening up pages
you can see what you have used last we
wanted to expose that also to uh al so
we have added the recent record virtual
table that you can query uh you can also
delete in there if you want to clean up
something um but overall other than the
deletion it's a read only which kind of
makes sense it's what you opened cost.
>> Awesome.
Next uh overall topic is the database
and uh because we are talking about the
database, I also put my on my tribute to
SQL Server t-shirt. The first we have
three things um and the first is a new
optimized data model for table
extensions. So many moons ago, prior to
version 23, we had a data model for
table extensions where each table
extension was stored in its own table.
And that mean meant that whenever you
needed to have read data from the base
and the table extension fields, that
would require a join on the database.
As of version 23, we optimized that so
that not one table extension for per
physical table, but we stored all the
table extension fields just in one
table. And that meant um that we could
go from an Nway join to one join. But
what's better than one join?
>> That is zero join.
>> Zero joins. So in this release we are
completing the story that we are now
putting all the table extensions fields
back on the base table. There will be no
more joints and this has some profound
benefits. The first is uh because no
joints uh the the read will be faster
but actually both delete, update, insert
and modify will be up to uh 30% faster.
You can see uh the different um numbers
here from our benchmark. Note that there
are of course different ways to read
data. Find first is just one. Um but
this should potentially speed up a lot
of database traffic. And with in many
cases performance or speed of loading
pages in business central uh in many
many cases it is bound to how much time
is spent on the database. So hopefully
with this users will just feel that
business central is just more snappy.
>> Yeah. Another thing that we did was um
completing our index management story.
>> Yeah. This was one of those stories we
started last release um and we got a
bunch of feedback. This was already a
feedback based thing. We have been asked
many years to make this and then we
presented it and we of course got more
feedback. Lovely. And uh there was all
of these things were actually based on
feedback. So let's just go through them.
Uh the thing first thing was well how do
you found this magical page where you
can disable indices? Um I kind of found
out that I hid it really well on the
table information page. Um so this time
we we looked at that where can we show
it and the first one is of course in
tell me. Uh I want to make a point here
that you can both find in normal tellme
by searching indexes or you can use the
advanced one via semantic search and you
will now be able to search on it based
on semantic meaning.
A a great example of this is I wrote
indices the British spelling and it also
came up here instead of just with the
American spelling of indexes. Um if we
click here index management we'll now
get a nice list where you select uh in
this case we'll select the GL entry and
when you then select it you get to the
page that was so well hidden before. One
of the things let's point out here
there's a new addition here. You can see
key 10 is there twice. It is both there
for the index that it makes but also for
the sift index. Uh let's try to see can
we disable that one. Yes, the button is
still visible which is a good sign.
Let's try to click it. And there you go.
A little box there. I hope you can see
it. Clearly shows the index is now
disabled in uh SQL. So no longer have
that impact of running with that index.
We have also another hidden thing that I
was told was no one really realized to
click the 254 there. So Kenny was
adamant that we add action up here that
makes it easier. So there's now the
manage indexes button.
>> But wait, there's more mess. Yeah,
that's so so one of those things that we
we really dreamed of was what about if
you have a feature that uses an index,
but most people don't use that feature.
It could be inventory. It could be
whatever. It could be something you add.
Well, now you can have that index define
it as enabled equal false. And then at
runtime add codes in the set.logic logic
that enables that key key here because
it's a key enable index is when it's in
the database. As you can see here from
the code example, you can both delete
disable them or enable them.
>> But wait, there's more.
>> There's always more. So the really big
thing what Kenny was talking about here,
we have one, we have one table now
instead of n or two, which also means we
can now add an index that spans both the
base table and your extension fields.
Another thing you have been asking of
for ages. So I hope you really enjoy
that. I I mean based on your feedback,
that was a really high up on there. So
I'm happy we could deliver that.
>> Awesome. And I think this actually
completes our backlog for index
management. uh we don't have any
anything else. So unless you also want
us to do something with the sole glob or
whatever then uh then this is considered
done.
Okay. And the final thing uh in the
database is that you can now use system
fields uh in analysis mode and also in
profiles. Now, system fields is an
ancient feature. Many many moons ago,
probably 10 release waves ago, we added
these uh last created by, created on,
last modified by, last modified on, and
a system ID to basically every single
table in Business Central. Um, and but
until now, those have been hidden in one
of my our most popular um an analytics
features, which is analysis mode. But
not anymore. Look, this is the the data
picker or the column picker in for an
analysis view and um and these new
system fields simply show up there even
though they are not uh shown on the
lists page and in that that means that
you can start uh having these I wouldn't
say audit reports but but still use this
data in your analysis views. So in this
particular example here I have the sales
order and um if I can just find my mouse
here we have added modified by and
modified at on the sales order. So you
can kind of have an idea if you're many
people in the sales team who was
touching which sales orders last.
Another place where you can use system
ids or system fields is in profiles. Um
here we have the page designer for
designing a profile. And if you search
on the field list for system, you'll
find the fields available. In this case,
you can see that I dragged in the
modified by here on the card. And if
that's your thing, that is now possible
to do. All right, this is going to be
the shortest paragraph of them all,
except for the next one. You see this
little icon
to the top right? This is because MCP
server has its completely own session uh
where you can learn uh much more about
all the things we did. So uh so this is
all you get in our presentation here.
MCP server is owned by our team. So we
thought we would give it a little bit of
attention in this what's new and for
server and database.
The same goes for reporting. reporting
also got three new um videos or so much
content or new features in reporting
that there are three videos for that. So
um if reporting is your thing uh you
should definitely go and watch that
after this. So stay with us.
And uh finally we have a couple of uh
small security improvements that uh came
because we are hardening everything in
business central the platform the client
the application and uh and we have these
two uh new uh smaller smaller things.
The first is uh in the last release wave
we added the new permissions overview
page which gives kind of this um
overview who can uh where is this
permission set used and you can filter
to a table or an application or a user
and um therefore we decided to reuse
this uh or give some more in context
actions. So uh to get to this page in in
the new version, you can start from the
permission sets list page from the
permission card or the table information
and then navigate to the permission
overview page in context of where you
were. So here's an example of that on
the permission set lists. Uh you now
have a link up here to the permission
overview
um here under actions. Same thing goes
on the permission set card. So you can
navigate through the where used um
action. And finally for the table
information, if you want to see which
permission sets is including or covering
a given table um then there's a
navigation from the table information to
the permissions uh overview.
Then the final thing we did was for um
auditing. Maybe not auditing, but uh if
you use telemetry uh for your business
central um telemetry can be used as as a
way to answer certain auditing questions
such as who did what when and in
particular we have had an ask for adding
telemetry on who did open in Excel.
the like the the best fraud example I
can come up with is a disgruntled
employee that opens the customer list or
the vendor lists exports it uh to Excel
before they leave uh because they got
fired last uh 5 minutes ago right with
this at least you would know who would
do such a thing so so that's uh there in
this RT 0056
tag in telemetry
and that's basically Ally it. Just one
more thing from us. If you want to know
more, we have some context specific
landing pages. MCP has this aka.ms/bcmcp
if that's your thing. If you want to
learn more about uh that all those new
goodies for uh developers or for um for
reporting that is aka.ms/bcde
developer and then navigate down to the
reporting section.
And for security, our landing page is as
always aka.ms/bc
security. And there you learn can learn
everything about how you can make
business central even more secure on uh
on all kinds of levels as seen from an
administrator, a partner, a user and so
on. That's that mass. Uh hope you have a
great launch edition with all the other
sessions. might see you at conferences
around the world to discuss all the
nitty-gritty details and feedback on the
things we do and love. Uh but we're
done.
>> Thank you.